Finding Aid for the William Horsley Papers LSC.0540
UCLA Library Special Collections
William Horsley papers
1903-1947
UCLA Library Special Collections
Horsley, Wm. (William)
LSC.0540
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
William Horsley (1870-1956) founded the Centaur Film Company (later, Nestor Motion Picture Company) in Bayonne, New Jersey in 1907. His film company and other independents merged to create Universal Pictures Company in 1912. The collection contains photographs, correspondence, magazines and magazine articles, and ephemera related to William Horsley's career in the motion picture industry.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. William Horsley, 1959.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9917205113606533
Biographical / Historical
Horsley was born in 1870; left England for the U.S.; worked as a boiler maker; with his brother David, founded the Centaur Film Company (later, Nestor Motion Picture Company) in Bayonne, New Jersey in 1907; along with his brother and other independents, founded Universal Pictures Company in 1912; designed and supervised the construction of Universal City; in 1916 he set up the Bill Horsley Laboratory (later, Hollywood Film Enterprises, Incorporated), which developed and printed 35mm. films; he died in 1956 in Los Angeles, California.
Biographical / Historical
William and David Horsley were pioneers in the motion-picture industry, starting in Bayonne, New Jersey, in 1907, under the name of Centaur Film Company (later Nestor Motion Picture Company). For the first three years, William was a silent partner, financing the little company which brother David was running. But from 1910 until 1916 he played an active role in the company running the laboratory part of the business. In 1916 he withdrew from the company and set up the Bill Horsley Laboratory, later known as Hollywood Film Enterprises, Inc., devoted exclusively to the developing and printing of 35mm. films.
He and his brother, along with other independents (notably Carl Laemmle and his Independent Motion Picture Company, known as IMPS, Swanson and Ed Porter) founded Universal Picture Company in 1912, and succeeded in defeating the monopolistic hold on the industry of the Patents Company and General Film Company (the famous Latham Loop controversy).
Scope and Content
Collection contains photographs, correspondence, magazines and magazine articles, and ephemera related to William Horsley's career in the motion picture industry. Also contains a one-page holograph autobiography by Horsley. Includes photographs of Horsley, Nestor Motion Picture Company staff, and the opening of Universal Studios. Journals, including Motive Power, feature biographical accounts of Horsley.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: William Horsley Papers (56 items).
Photographs.; Motion picture industry -- United States -- Archives.; Horsley, Wm. (William), -1956--Archives.; Universal Pictures Company.
- 56 photographs taken at the opening of Universal Studios, 1915. (Box 1)
- 2 photographs of William Horsley. (Box 1)
- A biography of David Horsley by William Horsley. In International Photographer, March-April 1934. (Box 1)
- National Photographic Dealer, August 1943. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Issue features William Horsley on the occasion of his 36th year in business.
- Motography, vol.13 no.1, pp.17-18., January 2, 1915. (Box 1)
  Article describing William Horsley's role in the establishment of Universal City.
- Bound volume of Motive Power, vol.1-2,, a monthly journal devoted to scientific boiler making., 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  William Horsley worked as a boiler maker shortly after arriving in this country from England and this publication contains a biographical sketch of him (vol.1, p.82), articles by him (vol.1, pp.90, 131, 136, 145, 150, 166, 177, 228; vol.2, p.10 [under the pseudonym of Nutmeg], 12, 48, 54, 68, 82, 92, 124, 175, 213)].
- Correspondence. (Box 1)
- Autobiography., 1p. holograph manuscript. (Box 1)
- Ephemera. (Box 1)
- Panoramic photographic of Nestor Motion Picture Company staff, Photo by Ramsey., December 23, 1911. (Box 2)
- David Horsley biography by Marc Wanamaker, Bison Archives, 1912 (Box 1)